*******************************************************************************
**** AVERTISSEMENT / WARNING
**** --------------------------------------------------------------
**** Même si des efforts sont déployés pour assurer la qualité des données 
**** et des métadonnées, nous ne pouvons garantir qu'aucune erreur ne s'y est 
**** glissée. Par conséquent, les données disponibles sur le site Nordicana D 
**** et dans le Polar Data Catalogue vous sont gracieusement fournies 
**** sans aucune forme de garantie.

**** Although efforts are made to ensure the quality of the data and 
**** metadata, we cannot guarantee that they contain no errors. Therefore, 
**** the data available on the CEN Nordicana D and on the Polar Data 
**** Catalogue websites are provided without a warranty of any kind.
*******************************************************************************



FICHIER DE DONNÉES / DATA FILE
--------------------------------------------------------------
nordicanad_arctic_and_red_fox_den_monitoring_data_1993-2019_berteaux.txt

TITRE / TITLE
--------------------------------------------------------------
Suivi de la reproduction du renard arctique et du renard roux à l’Île Bylot, Nunavut, Canada
Monitoring of arctic and red fox reproduction on Bylot Island, Nunavut, Canada

AUTEURS / AUTHORS
--------------------------------------------------------------
Dominique Berteaux
Département de Biologie & Centre d'études nordiques, Université du Québec à Rimouski

RÉSUMÉ / ABSTRACT
--------------------------------------------------------------
Les renards sont très dépendants de tanières, aussi bien pour la mise-bas que pour l’élevage des jeunes. Étant donné la faible épaisseur de la couche active du pergélisol dans la majorité de la zone de distribution du renard arctique, il est rare que de nouvelles tanières soient excavées et celles existantes sont souvent réutilisées année après année. Une manière efficace d’effectuer le suivi des populations de renards arctiques et de renards roux est donc de tirer partie de leur utilisation des tanières pour la reproduction.

Depuis 1993, les tanières de renards connues dans la plaine Sud de l’île Bylot ont été visitées chaque année de manière opportuniste afin de déterminer la présence de jeunes. À partir de 2003, le suivi est devenu systématique. Une recherche intensive des tanières a débuté jusqu’à recouvrir une aire d’environ 600 km2 s’étendant de la vallée de Qarlikturvik à la Pointe Dufour. Les tanières sont depuis visitées deux fois durant l’été, une fois à la mi-mai et une fois à la fin juin. Toutes les visites se font en moins d’une semaine afin de minimiser un double comptage de la même portée en cas de déménagement des jeunes lors de la période d’élevage. Seules les tanières avec des jeunes vus ou entendus sont catégorisées comme étant des tanières de reproduction (tanière natale ou tanière d’élevage). À partir de 2007, des appareils photo automatiques ont été posés sur certaines tanières afin de compléter les informations de terrain provenant des visites. 

#######

Foxes are strongly dependent on dens for parturition and rearing of cubs. Due to the shallow permafrost-free layer in most of the arctic fox’s range, new dens are rarely dug and existing ones are often used repeatedly year after year. An effective way to monitor both arctic and red fox populations is to take advantage of their use of den sites for reproduction.

Starting in 1993, known den sites in the south plain of Bylot Island were opportunistically visited to assess the presence of cubs. Starting from 2003, the monitoring became systematic. An extensive search of dens was conducted and covered an area of ca. 600 km2 going from the Qarlikturvik valley to Pointe Dufour. Since then, dens are visited twice during summer, once in mid-May and once at the end of June. All visits are made within a week to avoid counting the same litter twice due to relocation of cubs during the rearing period. Only dens where cubs are seen or heard are categorized as breeding dens (natal or rearing den). Since 2007, camera traps are installed on some dens to complement field observations.


CITATION DES DONNÉES / DATA CITATION
--------------------------------------------------------------
Berteaux, B. 2020. Suivi de la reproduction du renard arctique et du renard roux à l’Île Bylot, Nunavut, Canada, v. 1.1 (1993-2019). Nordicana D49, doi: 10.5885/45594CE-A69880E653314887.
Berteaux, B. 2020. Monitoring of arctic and red fox reproduction on Bylot Island, Nunavut, Canada, v. 1.1 (1993-2019). Nordicana D49, doi: 10.5885/45594CE-A69880E653314887.


SITE(S)
--------------------------------------------------------------

**** Camp 2, Île Bylot, Nunavut / Camp 2, Bylot Island, Nunavut ****
         Latitude:                   72.8885
         Longitude:                  -79.9061
         Altitude (m):               40

         Localisation / Location:
         ------------------------
             - Secteur situé à environ 30 km au sud de la Vallée Qarlikturvik.

             - Sector located about 30 km south of the Qarlikturvik Valley.

         Description:
         ------------
             - Ce secteur est caractérisé par une rivière glacière qui coule au milieu d’un plateau à basse altitude. De petits lacs, étangs et quelques milieux humides (polygones) sont présents le long de la rivière et de façon dispersé sur le plateau. L’habitat mésique se retrouve en abondance sur les versants de collines et le plateau. Une grosse colonie d’oies des neiges se trouve dans le secteur du Camp 2.

             - The sector is characterized by a low elevation plateau with a glacial river running through it. Small lakes, ponds and some wetlands (tundra polygons) are present along the river and on the plateau. Mesic tundra is abundant on slopes, hills and the plateau. A large snow goose colony is located in the Camp 2 area.


**** Camp 3, Île Bylot, Nunavut / Camp 3, Bylot Island, Nunavut ****
         Latitude:                   73.0473
         Longitude:                  -80.0775
         Altitude (m):               40

         Localisation / Location:
         ------------------------
             - Secteur situé à environ 15 km au sud de la Vallée Qarlikturvik.

             - Sector located about 15 km south of the Qarlikturvik Valley.

         Description:
         ------------
             - Une rivière parcourt une vallée encaissée entourée de collines jusqu’à 250 m d’altitude. Les plateaux sont dominés surtout par l’habitat mésique et on retrouve une zone de milieu humide à l’embouchure de la rivière près de la côte.

             - A river runs through a narrow valley surrounded by hills up to 250 m high. Elevated terraces are dominated mostly by mesic habitat and there is a wetland area at the mouth of the river near the coast.


**** Pointe Dufour, Île Bylot, Nunavut / Pointe Dufour, Bylot Island, Nunavut ****
         Latitude:                   72.7838
         Longitude:                  -79.5359
         Altitude (m):               55

         Localisation / Location:
         ------------------------
             - Secteur situé à environ 45 km au sud de la Vallée Qarlikturvik.

             - Sector located about 45 km south of the Qarlikturvik Valley.

         Description:
         ------------
             - Une rivière glacière parcourt cette vallée encaissée entourée de hautes collines. Ce site est dominé par une toundra mésique ou des crêtes xériques. On retrouve toutefois des petites parcelles de milieux humides dans les basses-terres.

             - A glacial river runs in a narrow valley surrounded by high hills. The area is dominated by mesic tundra or dry ridges but small wetland patches can be found in low-lying areas.


**** Vallée Qarlikturvik, Île Bylot, Nunavut / Qarlikturvik Valley, Bylot Island, Nunavut ****
         Latitude:                   73.1563
         Longitude:                  -79.9719
         Altitude (m):               20

         Localisation / Location:
         ------------------------
             - Six km de la côte, dans la plus grande vallée glaciaire de la plaine sud de l’Île Bylot

             - Six km inland, in the largest glacial valley of the south plain of Bylot Island

         Description:
         ------------
             - Le fond de la vallée est constitué d’un assemblage de polygones, de mares de fonte et d’étangs et de toundra à hummock mésique. La capacité de rétention d’eau de ces composantes topographiques, combinée à la faible capacité de drainage du pergélisol, contribue à la formation des milieux humides de la vallée. On retrouve les habitats plus secs de type mésique sur les contours des polygones, les sites mieux drainés en fond de vallée et sur les versants des collines et les plateaux qui entourent les basses-terres de la vallée. La station principale de recherche est située au milieu de la Vallée Qarlikturvik.

             - The valley bottom consists of an assemblage of tundra polygons, thaw lakes and ponds and mesic hummocky tundra. The water retaining capacity of these topographical features and the poor drainage of the underlying permafrost contribute to the formation of wetlands in the valley. Dryer areas dominated my mesic tundra are found on the rims surrounding polygons, better-drained sites in the valley bottom and on slopes, hills and elevated terraces surrounding the valley lowlands. The main field station is located in the center of the Qarlikturvik Valley.


DONNÉES / DATA
--------------------------------------------------------------

**** Année d'étude / Study year ****
    - Année
    - Year


**** Commentaires / Comments ****
    - Commentaires
    - Comments


**** Espèce de renard utilisant la tanière / Fox species using the den ****
    - Renard arctique
Renard roux
    - Arctic fox
Red fox



**** Numéro de la portée / Litter number ****
    - Numéro de la portée
    - Litter number


**** Numéro de la tanière / Den number ****
    - FOX0XX: Dens at Qarlikturvik Valley
FOX1XX: Dens at Camp 2
FOX3XX: Dens at Camp 3
FOX2XX: Dens at Pointe Dufour
FOX4XX: Dens at the northern limit of Qarlikturvik Valley (out of study area)

    - FOX0XX: Dens at Qarlikturvik Valley
FOX1XX: Dens at Camp 2
FOX3XX: Dens at Camp 3
FOX2XX: Dens at Pointe Dufour
FOX4XX: Dens at the northern limit of Qarlikturvik Valley (out of study area)


**** Statut reproducteur de la tanière / Reproductive status of the den ****
    - NM: Not monitored: den known but not visited
NR: Non reproductive: no cubs were seen on the den or heard inside the den
N (Natal): cubs were seen or heard inside the den
R (Rearing): cubs were moved to the den later in the season. The associated natal den can be determined if tagged adults or tagged cubs were seen on the rearing den. In some cases, if the cubs seemed old when they were first spotted on a den that was previously inactive, the den was categorized as a rearing den (but with no associated natal den)
C (Collapsed): holes became covered with soil or the den collapsed and disappeared; a collapsed den is not monitored after it is collapsed

    - NM: Not monitored: den known but not visited
NR: Non reproductive: no cubs were seen on the den or heard inside the den
N (Natal): cubs were seen or heard inside the den
R (Rearing): cubs were moved to the den later in the season. The associated natal den can be determined if tagged adults or tagged cubs were seen on the rearing den. In some cases, if the cubs seemed old when they were first spotted on a den that was previously inactive, the den was categorized as a rearing den (but with no associated natal den)
C (Collapsed): holes became covered with soil or the den collapsed and disappeared; a collapsed den is not monitored after it is collapsed


INSTRUMENTS
--------------------------------------------------------------

FORMAT DU FICHIER DE DONNÉES / DATA FILE FORMAT
--------------------------------------------------------------

**** Type de fichier / File type ****
      Texte avec tabulateur / Tab delimited text

**** Code de donnée manquante / Missing data code ****
      NA

**** Dates et heures / Dates and hours ****
      Local / Local

**** Définition des colonnes / Column definition ****
1----------> Année d'étude/Study year [Année/Year]
2----------> Numéro de la tanière/Den number
3----------> Statut reproducteur de la tanière/Reproductive status of the den
4----------> Espèce de renard utilisant la tanière/Fox species using the den
5----------> Numéro de la portée/Litter number
6----------> Commentaires/Comments




